So we all travel and it is
very important to take travel insurance for international travel,
so travel
insurance protects you,
suppose there is a problem in a foreign country,
you are going to another country, there is a
medical emergency, your passport is
lost, your baggage is lost, you have any
personal liability, suppose you cause
harm to someone, then the responsibility of that responsibility lies with the
insurance company,
if you take a travel insurance policy,
then today we will cover this in this video,
I am making a travel insurance digest, where we will talk about what is included and
what is
excluded in the frequency of travel insurance, so this is a standard
list, but you must refer to the document of the travel insurance
policy that you go to take,
what are its
features, so I will share this standard list
with you and explain everything, it will be a
very useful video because
you know that travel is increasing continuously
and travel insurance is an important part of
your travel itinerary, start the video
Before that, I would like to introduce myself.
My name is Gurleen Ka
Tikku. I am a Certified Financial Panner. I have been
associated with the insurance industry for the last 19 years and every week I
bring videos for you so that your
personal financial life can become easy and happy
and the journey of insurance mind can also
become easy and happy because the tagline of our company
is Creating a Wealth of
Happiness. Quick reminder before starting the video.
If you have
not yet subscribed to our channel, do it so that
you get the right information at the right
time. Now let's talk. First, we will talk about
when you are going to take travel insurance, it is
very important for you to tell your pre-exit medical history there too. So,
a line is clearly written in a travel insurance that
any pre-exit condition whether
disclosed or not disclosed will not be
covered in the policy, meaning if
you have blood pressure or diabetes,
if there is any complication related to it, any
medical emergency occurs in another country, then
it will not be covered even if you have that blood
pressure.  Whether you disclose your diabetes or not,
if at the time of hospitalization it is
found that it was a pre-existing condition and got aggravated due to that and
you had to be hospitalized, then
it will not be covered, so
you should keep this in mind that claim for pre-existing
conditions is not available
in travel insurance. Now we will quickly talk about
some frequency
which you people ask, firstly, after you
take a travel insurance policy,
your question is that I have to make
some changes in the policy, suppose the
travel date has to be changed or some
information has been filled incorrectly, then can an endorsement be done, yes, you
can definitely get an endorsement done, you should reach out to the insurance company,
attach your revised travel dates, your revised ticket and you
can get an endorsement done, if you have to modify any basic
details like name is wrong,
address is wrong, then attach proof
and it gets modified, you have to mail it
to the insurance company and they will quickly
give it to you after modifying it, secondly, these people
ask that if the travel insurance policy which
you have taken,  So, if your travel
plans are cancelled, do you get a refund? You
definitely get a refund. You will have to provide proof
that you are not travelling.
You will have to provide proof of cancellation
that you had a travel plan but it got cancelled due to any reason. To get a
refund, you will
also have to provide scanned pages of your passport or
your complete passport booklet as
proof that you did not travel
on those dates. There are cancellation charges of
approximately ₹ and the remaining premium is
refunded to you.
You will hear a very common term in travel insurance,
deductible or excess deductible. Basically,
before paying any claim, you will pay an amount. Suppose it is written that there is a
deductible of $10000. This means
that any claim comes with an initial amount of $100. Let's take an
example, if there is a claim of $500, then the
initial amount will be $100.  You have to pay and the
insurance company will pay the remaining $400 up to the initial sum insured. If
any claim is
taken at any time, the deduction will be written in every claim. It will be
clearly mentioned in your policy document
and this is applicable for all the
claims. Next, your question arises
whether you can extend your travel insurance.
Generally, what happens is that if
you travel for 30 days and your
plan gets extended, then your
travel insurance will expire after 30 days. So,
your question arises whether you
can extend it. Yes, you
can definitely extend it. There are some
conditions for it. First, your due date has
not yet crossed, which means your 30 days are
not completed. Before that, you have to
intimate the insurance company that my
stay has been extended and I want to extend my travel
insurance. Second, you have
not made any claim in the policy. It is
subject to claim. Your sum assured remains
unchanged. Suppose you have a
policy of $50,000.  If you had taken the insurance and you
want to extend it, then that
is possible. Now, if you say that you want to enhance the sum assured, then
perhaps the insurance company will not extend your policy because they will doubt that
you want to take a claim. Fourth,
you will be asked for a declaration of good health
that you are in good health and your
health is absolutely good. On that basis, your
policy will be extended. So, next, a very
common question is that if the
contact numbers are mentioned below in the claim,
whom you have to contact
in case of emergency, contact number, email
ID, international numbers are also mentioned
and Indian numbers are also mentioned, so
you will contact there whenever you have a
medical emergency or you have to take a
claim from this policy and if there is any such
claim like personal liability or
loss of passport, loss of baggage, you can also send an email. There is a
very quick
response on mail also in travel insurance
policies. And one more thing you have to keep in mind is
that whenever you are making a claim from travel insurance, whatever amount
you have
Original documents are there like boarding
pass, if you have any medical bills
available there, if you have any reports or
test reports, suppose
in case of loss of baggage or loss of
passport, if you have got a receipt issued to the authorities
or had given them the first information
that this has been lost, information of loss, then
you should maintain the file of all these documents
till the final claim is settled, they can ask
for anything, so
you will retain the original document with you even after coming to India
till your full and
final claim settlement is not done, so now we will
talk about what is excluded in the policy
because it is important to know when you are
taking travel insurance, everything
cannot be included, some things will be excluded,
so what are the general exclusions
of travel insurance, we will
talk about that, first any body injury
or sickness means any injury or sickness to your body due to
civil war or foreign war,
then it will not be covered, company risk is
not covered  Secondly, if there is a body injury or
illness because of intentional
injury, it means your intention was wrong and because of that
you got the illness or your intention
was not right and because of that you got that body
injury, you can also call it self-infliction.
Suppose the biggest example is
someone who smokes excessively and because of that his
lungs got damaged, then in that case the
insurance company will not pay the claim because the intention was not right. The
second
example is any alcohol abuser, the
company will not cover because there is a clause
that if your intention is not right or you are
provoking your intention, then you will
not get the claim. Thirdly, if there is self-infliction, it
means you are going against medical advice, you are
doing something that
you know can put you in danger,
unless you are going to save someone's life, that is a
different matter, but other than that, if that body
injury occurs due to this reason, you know
that  Even if it is dangerous, the
insurance company will not give the claim. Next
is under the influence of alcohol and drug
abuse, meaning if you are an excessive alcohol or
drug abuser, the
policy will not give you the claim. Next is if there is
any body injury where you are
participating in any competition, you
can call it adventure sports, motor sports
or air sports, you are participating in some such competition
where you know that there
is danger, even there the insurance
company will not give you the claim. Next point is if
you are riding a bike which is
above 150 cc, even if you have an
accident there, the insurance company will
not give the claim. Next is if there is any body
injury or sickness where you
are involved in a criminal act, even if your
intention is not right, the insurance company will
not give the claim. Next is if you
are carrying, meaning if you are pregnant and
within these 26 weeks you have a body injury or
sickness, even then the insurance company will
not give the claim. Next is if there is any body
injury where you  If you
participate in the military forces,
participate in the police force, wherever
you come across these police personnel and military
forces, then claim is not
given there. Suppose you are practicing and
undergoing training to become one, then
if any loss occurs there, the
company will not cover it because it is an
occupational hazard. Next, which I
told you in the beginning itself, any
medical expenses arising because of a
pre-existing medical condition, that is, if you have to
incur any medical expense due to any pre-existing medical condition, then the
insurance company will not cover it. If there is any
pathological fracture, a pathological
fracture is basically a fracture which
occurs due to which, that means if your bone is weak because
of any cancer, because
of any tumor, your bone is weak due to which
that fracture occurred, then
also the claim will not be paid. Last
but not the least, this list is not extensive, there
may be more exclusions in other companies, but this is a standard list which
I have shared with you.  Which is generally
not payable, so in the end, if
you have a bodily injury or an
accident due to terrorism, then it is not covered
in travel insurance policies. Now you will
say that many things are not covered, then are they
covered? Now let us talk about inclusions, whether they
are covered or not. Many
things are covered as well, but understand that
insurance is a very deep
contract, so it is important for you to know
what things will not be covered in your policy. We had
talked about this earlier,
now we will talk about what things
are included and believe me, the list of inclusions
is longer than exclusions, so more
things are included, rest assured,
first is accidental death. If there is an accidental
death, if there is an accident and within
12 months, the
direct reason for which was an accident, means, due to the accident,
some ripples occurred,
due to that something happened which would result in
death within 12 months, then you will get an accidental death
claim.  Next is permanent disability, which
means permanent disability due to an accident
within 12 months of the accident. If the accident is directly related to the accident
and it causes permanent disability, then
also the claim will be paid. There is a table for that which
I am sharing on the screen in front of you.
You can refer to this table. According to this table, the
claim will be paid to you. That percentage will be paid to
you on the claim. So, for example,
100% compensation will be given for permanent total disability.
Permanent and in-curable, these
can be called mental illness, 100% will be given.
Permanent total loss of two limbs
100% sight in both eyes 100%. So these are the
conditions where you become permanently disabled and
you will not be able to work properly.
If this loss occurs, then next is
permanent total loss of speech, permanent
removal of lower jaw or permanent total loss
of hearing in both years.  75% claim will be given for
total loss of one limb, then 50%
claim will be given for 50% loss of one eye. Whichever loss
you choose, any loss that is
irrecoverable is called permanent.
Temporary is that which is for some time
and will be recovered in the future. So
if there is an irrecoverable loss, then your claim will be paid in this percentage.
So now we will
see further. There are some other tables also which you
can refer to. I will not talk about all the details
but you can refer to these tables. For example,
suppose someone's finger is broken, a
permanent loss of one finger. If there are three
joints, then 5%, if there are two joints, then
3.5%, if there is one joint, then 2%. So you can take it like this,
from 2% to 100% compensation
is available. If this loss occurs, then next
is emergency medical expenses. Just now we
talked about death. Now let us talk about
medical expenses if you have a medical
emergency or have to consult a doctor.
Or if you have to be hospitalized, then
its expenses will be
borne by your insurance company up to some extent.
Keep in mind the deductible here, that is,
how much deductible is mentioned in your policy,
they will give you claim only above that. So what will be
covered here basically, so
whatever is your physician's fee will be covered,
so your hospital room
charges and treatment charges,
surgical charges, all will be covered,
if there are any ambulance charges, then those will also be
covered, if you are getting any
diagnostic test done which is necessary
related to your hospitalization or
treatment, then that will also be covered
and the expenses of registered nurse,
whatever will be the expense of registered nurse will also be
covered, so here
this thing will be covered in medical expenses, but there are
some things which you have to keep in mind due to
which your claim can be non-payable,
firstly, the advice you take should be from a registered
medical practitioner, otherwise the
claim will not be paid, secondly, if your
intention to travel is for medical
tourism  If you are traveling, suppose
you were going for treatment, then the
insurance company will not pay the money because
you did not disclose that
before taking the travel insurance and that thing is
also not covered in travel insurance. Next, suppose
you have taken a policy, let's take an example,
you have taken a policy in Singapore
and you go for treatment in the US, then the
insurance company will not pay the claim
because you know that travel
insurance
charges premium according to the territory where you are traveling, so
you paid the premium for Asia
and you are getting treatment in the US,
then the insurance company will not pay the claim.
Next, any expense which is a
medical expense before the policy starts, that will not be payable.
Next is emergency dental treatment,
so there is a difference between dental treatment and emergency dental
treatment. A dental
treatment may be that you need to get a root canal done,
you may need to get
scaling done or cleaning done,
but emergency dental treatment is
where there is acute pain, meaning you
cannot bear it till you return to your country,
you are in severe pain due to which
you will have to take dental treatment or visit a
dental doctor.  You will have to take
consultation with a dentist, so
dental treatment is covered there.
Next is emergency travel benefits. The
first point here is medical repatriation.
It means that suppose you
went to another country and there you needed medical
treatment. Suppose you had gone there for a
month but your health
deteriorated there. After one month, you underwent medical
treatment and after the treatment, you are
not in a position to continue your journey. You will
not be able to stay there for the remaining two months
because of your medical
treatment. So, the company gives you the medical
repatriation expenses, which will be the
actual expense or the amount
mentioned in the policy schedule. The
amount of time short is mentioned in it, which is payable in it.
Whichever is less, the insurance company will
give it to you and will take you to your home. Next
is body repatriation. It means
that if someone goes abroad and unfortunately
dies, then in that case, the insurance
company bears the cost of bringing your body
to the destination from where you
came.  So,
basically, the
insurance company bears the actual cost of bringing them back. This is
mentioned in short in your policy schedule.
Or the actual cost of repatriation,
whichever is less, will be
borne by the insurance company. So, here, it is
important to inform the insurance company.
Suppose, in both these conditions, you
need this repatriation help. Whether you
are the policyholder yourself or their family
members are seeking repatriation help, then it is
very important to inform the insurance company. Suppose, you went and
you have made your own arrangements that we will take you
back or you will go back.
After that, you are informing the insurance company. So,
before making assistance arrangements, it is possible that the
insurance company may not pay your claim. So, the
first step is to contact them so that
they can make their own arrangements.
Next is contingent travel
benefits. So, here, basically,
due to your medical treatment, you are hospitalized for more than five days
and you miss your flight
home.  A because you were
not medically fit to go, then the
insurance company will cover you there and here
also you will get
assistance, so you should check whether
this benefit is there in it or not when you are taking the policy, so
check the schedule of benefits once
before taking any travel insurance policy, next
is accidental death common carrier, so common
carrier is basically if you are travelling by land, air or water
and if
during that time death occurs due to an accident, then within
these 12 months if it is directly
related to it, if death occurs due to that reason, then the
insurance company will give the claim to you or
your legal representative, then the
insurance company will give the claim to the
beneficiary in the policy holder, second
permanent disability common carrier, if while
travelling in this common carrier, like cha bhai,
you are travelling by road, land, air or by water
and some accident happens
and an accident occurs, then within
these 12 months if any disability directly related to it occurs, then  The
insurance
company will pay the claim here. Again, regarding permanent
disability, which we had discussed, tables will be
applicable to show how much loss is there, what
percentage claim you will get, hospital cash will be given, suppose
you get hospitalized, then
your insurance company will also give you daily cash benefit,
if this clause is
included in your policy, then loss of baggage
and personal documents, suppose your
baggage gets lost by a common carrier, now you are going to the buyer
and your luggage which you had checked in, suppose
if the checked in baggage gets
lost by the airline, then you have to
inform the insurance company about the
limit mentioned in your policy, the limit will be
mentioned that
we will cover checked and baggage only up to this amount, so that amount of checked and baggage will be
reimbursed to you on
proving that it has actually happened.
Flight delay is also covered where
if your flight gets delayed due to any
circumstances, where the airline has
delayed the flight after a few number of years,
that is mentioned in your policy.  You
also get compensation, so
hijacking is also a clause which
also covers the cost of hijacking, suppose if the plane is hijacked, then the
inconvenience you faced there, for
how long you remained under hijacking, that too is
paid out to you. Now you can see here
that deductible will definitely be applicable, that is, if the
initial amount will not be paid, then the
amount above that will be paid. Next is personal
liability. We have just talked about personal liability, which
can be our medical emergency or
personal belongings can be lost. Now let's talk about
personal liability. Suppose,
due to you, someone has suffered loss, to a
human being or to someone's property, then
in that case, an insurance company is the compensator. Let's
see what all is covered for you. So,
property damage is covered. If due to you,
someone's property gets damaged
unintentionally, then in that case, the insurance
company will cover it. What are the exclusions here? The
first exclusion is if you had intentionally
tried to harm someone,
your intention was to damage a human being or any
property, then the insurance
company is not liable to give the claim.  For this,
that personal liability is your own. Secondly,
if that property is your own, then it is
not a third party liability. It is
your own property, so the insurance
company is not liable. Personal liability is
towards third party if there is damage to someone else's
property. Thirdly,
if you are in such a business that due to the
nature of your business, someone has an
accident or their property gets damaged, then
Insurance company is not liable.
Any liability is such where you had to
provide some professional services to someone which you could
not provide and due to which he is
asking compensation from you to a third person, then the
insurance company is not liable because it was
your professional duty which you did
not complete. Here it is basically that due to your mistake,
you did not have the intention but
this loss happened because of any such mistake of yours, and if it was an unintentional mistake, then only if it is happening
because of an unintentional mistake, then the
insurance company will give the claim, otherwise it will
not give the claim. Next is loss of
passport. Suppose your passport is lost,
your personal belongings are lost, then
there also you get support from the
insurance company, your limit is
specified there, you have to inform the right authorities,
complain to the police
and there is a process, through that process
you can make this claim. Last
emergency financial assistance is provided
where someone steals your personal belongings
and steals your money.  Even if
you don't have money to
continue your journey, the insurance
company will provide you some financial
assistance, inclusions, and exclusions of
the policy. I answered some frequency.
So, look here, after taking everything out and getting the
crux out, it is
important that you check your insurance policy
before going. That means, don't just see which
policy is cheaper and buy that one. Just understand
what is covered and what is
not covered. It is better to
take a policy with more coverage because if
you are paying the premium of the policy
in rupees, but the benefits you are getting are
in dollars. So, make sure that you
take the right decision and
you should take a policy with maximum coverage. And
yes, this is a standard list. You
must check your specific policy which
you are going to take. And if you
found the video useful, then share it
with friends and family. And don't forget to subscribe to us.
Thank you so much for watching
our videos. Stay safe, take care. Bye, bye,
see you soon.
[music]